so thanks everybody for um joining this week's
uh magnet seminar um it's in in a nice uh late
uh or mid uh august uh schedule we've had a bit of
a disruption in the last couple of weeks with some
uh schedule shifts but um we're getting back on
to track again and that's the quick reminder for
people who haven't come to market seminar before
we have presentations that are about 30 minutes
long or so so we kindly ask that you keep your
microphones muted during the presentation so it's
not to disturb the presenter if you have problems
with your internet connection we recommend
turning off your video to allow better bandwidth
and at the end of the presentations we'll have
10 to 15 minutes um for questions and discussions
and you're welcome to to unmute and ask a question
but if you also want to just ask question by
text you can type it into the chat and i can
read it out for you as always uh life is going on
around us right now many of us are at home so you
have if you have to get up and go please just uh
get up and go uh that doesn't apply to you dave
you have to stay for the duration um but at the
end of it all uh we'll have a chance to uh have
a catch-up and a bit of a social at the end and
that part of our seminars uh it isn't recorded
and so today i'm really pleased to have uh
dave heslop from australia australia national
university who will be talking about uncertainty
propagation in paleomagnetic data so i will hand
over to you dave okay thanks greg so let me share
my screen and okay can you see that okay that's
perfect yeah okay well like i said thanks greg and
thanks for the invitation to give this um seminar
so as advertised i'm going to be talking about
simple uncertainty propagation for paleomagnetic
data and this is something that andrew and i
have been working on for a few years now and
importantly acknowledge the sponsors so this was
actually funded by the australian research council
now a lot of the things i talk about at the
beginning are going to be pretty familiar to you
and it's no big surprise that paleomagnetism
kind of has a hierarchical structure both in the
way that we deal with samples and specimens and
sites but also in the way that we do with our data
so i've got my little schematic here that
you know we collect specimens from a site
and or samples and then maybe we're averaging
samples to get some kind of sight mean direction
and then maybe we're averaging site
mean directions to get formation means
and maybe we're going from formation means to
paleomagnetic poles and then onto apparent polar
wonder path so we're really dealing with this
hierarchical structure throughout paleomagnetism
so in terms of the data processing i'm going
to refer to this as a data processing chain
not surprisingly that's hierarchical as well
so when we start at the the bottom of the data
processing chain we've got things like specimen
remnants directions that we'd assess using pca
and maximum angular deviations
and we're maybe combining specimen
directions to give us a slight mean
direction using typically fischer
statistics but maybe a bootstrap if you've
got sufficient observations available to you
then we could be combining into formation means
paleomagnetic poles apparent polar wonder paths
typically like i said always using vicious
statistics so within this data processing chain
or this hierarchy information is always going from
the bottom specimen remnants directions through to
the top and although we do assess uncertainty at
these different levels so of course with vicious
statistics we're talking about things like alpha
95s remnants directions we're maybe using mads
typically we don't actually propagate that
uncertainty so we don't consider the mads and
our specimen directions and think what effect
does that have on our site mean directions
maybe if we've got a collection of site mean
directions with their alpha 95s when we then
calculate a formation mean direction we just
ignore those site mean alpha 95s and just
carry on with our estimation of a mean so we don't
actually propagate those uncertainties through
now it's not as though we ignore the uncertainties
completely because we do use things like
mads and alpha 95s maybe a selection criteria if
i'm looking at a specimen remnants direction and
my mads over some value like 10 degrees maybe i
said well probably that's not very good and i just
remove it from the analysis similarly if my alpha
95 is very large maybe i think i won't include
that site so we do use these uncertainties but
we don't actually propagate them so the aims of
the project that andrew and i was working on were
to do what i was just talking about come up with
an error propagation scheme that can move through
or give us a way to propagate uncertainty through
this paleomagnetic data processing chain and
we set ourselves a couple of targets as well we
wanted it to be as simple as possible am i simple
i mean that you don't need some really complex
bespoke code for doing this rather it's something
that people can just code up themselves in excel
the other important thing was we wanted it to
apply to legacy data often with legacy data
you don't have full demagnetization information
available by which i mean individual thermal or
afd magnetization steps so what we wanted was a
way to propagate uncertainties from the specimen
level without actually having full demagnetization
information available now a bit of a spoiler alert
we've always we've already published the um the
paper on this so if you're interested in some
more of the details this is the paper you need
to look for it's in jgr last year uncertainty
propagation and hierarchy called paleomagnetic
reconstructions and obviously i don't have time to
go into all the details here so the paper is where
you need to look so what i'm going to talk about
is underpinned by the fischer distribution again
something familiar to all of us as paleomagnetists
um here's the equation for the fischer
distribution as defined in fish's 1953 paper this
is in its matrix form where we're using cartesian
coordinates but the key thing is the distribution
is defined by a mean and mu and kappa which is the
concentration so the distribution's rotationally
symmetric by which i mean it has circular contours
around the mean and just to give you an idea of
what the concentration parameter is doing if you
imagine i've sliced through a sphere here and i've
got a fischer distribution in blue then when kappa
is is low my distribution is very broad and may
actually wrap the whole way around the sphere and
as kappa increases the distribution gets narrower
and narrower until we reach a point as we're
moving towards infinity where the distribution
is infinitely thin but broadly speaking with
kappa is just the width of the distribution
now in his 1953 paper fisher gave what we call
maximum likelihood estimates of how for a given
set of directions so imagine we have n directions
which are represented by a collection of
unit vectors just in cartesian coordinates x
y and z how we can estimate the mean and the
concentration of the fissure
distribution that best fits that data
and this is nothing new if you look in
any paleomagnetism textbook you'll see
these equations first thing we do is estimate the
resultant vector length we get by adding together
all of these unit vector observations
so we just add together the x components
square them add together the y component
square them said components square them add
them all together take the square root that's our
resultant vector length okay no big surprise there
and then once we've got that resultant vector
length we can just deal again with the x
y and z components and this will give us our mean
direction of the best fitting distribution and the
mean is mu now we also need to work out kappa
this is an expression that maybe isn't quite
as familiar because it's typically not given in
the textbooks but this was the expression fischer
developed that relates the resultant vector length
to the concentration now the difficulty here
is that you can't actually solve this
equation in an analytical form if you know
r you can't solve for kappa so what fischer did
was come up with an approximation for estimating
kappa which is the one at the top here which again
is the familiar one that we see in textbooks where
it's simply n minus one over n minus r so this is
the approximate solution to this equation and it
works when we have higher concentrations
when kappa equals is greater than 3.
subsequently for example banerjee at al 2005 have
come up with a better approximation for kappa
you can see it's still just a function of n
and r so i'm actually going to work with this
expression from banerjee but you could
imagine working with fish's original
expression and it's not going to
make a huge amount of difference
now that's the fischer distribution in cartesian
coordinates but of course we can also work in
spherical coordinates as well inclination
declination again here's our expression
for uh kappa as a function of uh resultant
vector length which in this case is called a
now you may be thinking dave why are you showing
us the same set of equations with slightly
different nomenclature and they're all fuzzy
and this is maybe one thing if nothing else you
remember from this talk this is maybe one thing
you remember these come from the phd of arnold
phd thesis in 1941 on the spherical probability
distributions phd thesis from mit so fischer did
not discover the fischer distribution arnold
discovered the fischer distribution in 1941.
for continuity i will refer to it as the fischer
distribution for the remainder of the torque
so when we've got our efficient distribution
how do we actually deal with uncertainty
given n and r that we saw in a few slides
ago we calculate an alpha 95 again we find
this in all our paleomagnetic textbooks and
this was something that appeared in fischer's
1953 paper so the alpha 95 is this cone
of confidence around the mean that means
there's a 95 probability that the true
mean of the data actually lies somewhere
within the alpha 95 okay again very familiar
form but what's this actually based on
what fishes showed is that if we have a
collection of data and we estimate the mean and
the concentration okay then we've got the best
fit to the observations so we've got a fissure
distribution with a mean of mu and a concentration
of kappa but of course we don't know the true mean
all we've done is estimate the mean based on
the observations that we have available to us
so the distribution of the true mean
direction is also fissure distributed
centered on our estimated mean but with
a precision or a concentration equal to
kappa multiplied by r so we've now actually got a
probability distribution that itself is a fischer
distribution describing the uh probability
distribution of the true mean direction
so if we imagine let's try and do some error
propagation we're going to take two site mean
directions and combine them together so we've got
site a which is efficient distribution it's got
its own mean and the distribution of the mean
controlled by the concentration kappa a and
r a and then the same thing for b but i've just
used the b's here to indicate i'm working on site
b now if we were working with standard gaussian
statistics we could just add together the gaussian
distributions and we'd get a a resultant calcium
distribution and that's great makes things really
simple that's what a lot of error propagation
is based on that you add two gaussians together
you get another gaussian the challenge with the
fischer distribution is that if you add together
two fischer distributions such as our site
means here you don't get a fischer distribution
so immediately that means that simple hierarchical
error propagation is not possible because if for
example we combine site mean directions we don't
get another fischer distribution and we can't then
calculate a formation mean based on fisher
statistics so we could throw our hands up in
the air and say well this is impossible but maybe
we also need a healthy spoonful of pragmatism
and what we actually find is that if you add
together two fischer distributions you don't
get efficient distribution but you
will get something that's pretty
close to a fishy distribution so like i said
with this spoonful of pragmatism what we can
do is use a technique called moment matching
to find which fit which fischer distribution
best approximates the sum of a collection of
fisher distributions now i'm not going to go into
the details of moment matching that's in the paper
but what i will do is show you how this works
so again imagine we've got n site mean directions
and we want to take that average but also
propagate in the uncertainty associated with each
site mean direction now for each site we calculate
a weighting term rho that is just a function of
kappa and r from that site mean direction now you
may remember this from the definitions by fischer
and arnold this just corresponds to the resultant
vector length so what we're doing is representing
that distribution fischer distribution on the mean
as a vector with its length defined according
to the expected vector length for a certain
concentration in a fischer distribution
so for each site we calculate the row term
and then we find the weighted mean of
those n site directions simply using
our weighting terms for each site as we
combine the x components to get a resultant
vector length for the combination of all n site
mean directions so this slides very equationally
but what you can see is really this is exactly
the same as the fischer statistics we talked about
earlier all i've done is add in a waiting term for
each site once i've got that i can calculate my
mean direction from my combination of site means
again just by adding in my weighting term i can
calculate a kappa and i can calculate an alpha 95
that now just employs this resultant vector length
where things have been combined according to
their weight terms so what i've done here like
i said the equations are exactly the same apart
from this addition of this simple waiting term
and i've marked this with a little star indicating
that this is an alpha 95 that contains error
propagation okay so now we've got a way that
we can combine together site mean directions
with their uncertainties into an average site
mean direction with a propagated uncertainty
and importantly the result is fishy distributed
so we can continue up the hierarchy once i've
got an answer from this averaging i
can compare it with other averagings
i can get formation means and so on because
everything stays as efficient distribution
now we need to take a step
back um i've been talking
about um site level and site means but what
about the specimen level analysis now of course
typically for specimen level
analysis we're talking about
pca fits through demagnetization data as um
suggested by coach joe kirschbink in 1980 um
and we get our maximum angular deviations now
as i mentioned earlier in my talk typically we
use these for quality control if my mads over
a certain value we maybe throw the specimen
out of our analysis but if we want to use this
mad as a measure of uncertainty we've got to
find some way to convert it into a probability
distribution so working with mads by themselves
is not very obvious what kind of uncertainty
they actually represent so somehow we've got
to convert this into a probability distribution
so that we can include it in our error analysis
now this is uh a piece of work andrew and i did i
think it was published in 2016 where we we placed
principal component analysis in a full bayesian
framework in order that we could estimate uh
the uncertainties associated with these specimen
level directions this is difficult for a number
of reasons the first one that goes kind of against
our project aims is in order to do this you need
full demagnetization data which isn't always
available in the case of legacy data sets and
to be honest the algorithm to do this is pretty
nasty okay so if you read the paper you'll see
all these horrible equations and it isn't a simple
analysis to implement so this isn't something that
realistically we can use when we're trying to
come up with a simple error propagation scheme
but rather there's this really nice paper
by kokoloff and herlow and i i think this
paper is kind of under appreciated so you can see
that the title from the title this is going to be
particularly helpful principal component analysis
of paleomagnetic directions converting an mad
into an alpha 95 angle this is great and what
they showed through a collection of simulations
was that when you do pca analysis on um
your paleomagnetic or your demagnetization data
the uncertainty on the mean direction that you get
from that pca is visually distributed so this
is great because that means it's going to fit
into our general scheme of propagating fissure
distributions and what they showed is that mad
can be rescaled to an alpha 95 and this is
really easy to do based on this table that
they provided so for example if in your pca you
included five demagnetization steps in your fit
and you um you calculate your mad and
then to get your alpha 95 you just
multiply your mad by 3.18 in the case where you
didn't use an anchored fit but if you used an
anchored fit then you need to multiply it by 4.63
this is a really easy system to use and hopefully
it means that in the case of legacy data we can
actually still estimate these alpha 95s because as
long as we have the inclination declination number
of demagnetization steps and if we know if it was
anchored or unanchored then we can get an alpha
95 without having the full demagnetization data
so we've now got a way to convert specimen level
uncertainty into fissure distributions and then as
i showed we can just keep propagating that through
by using this weighting scheme in order to find
the best approximating fissure distribution
so i'm going to show you some examples
uh this is an example by bihar ital in 2019 where
they were looking at psv from the golan heights
um and i should say at this point i'm showing
these examples not because i'm disputing
the findings of these papers or i've got any
complaints about them it's because the data is
particularly demonstrative and importantly they
uploaded it to the magic database so i was able
to download it and and work with it so we're going
to look at the first site here what you can see is
the site mean directions based on seven specimens
which is pretty good you can see a lot of the
specimens have a high number of demagnetization
steps included in their pca so anywhere up to 19
11 9 that's a that's a reasonable number of
demagnetization steps and the mads associated with
the um with the pca fits are all pretty small so
we do our fischer propagation of the uncertainties
from the specimen into the site level mean
and what we find is if we just calculated the
site mean in the traditional way without error
propagation we get an alpha 95 of 4.7 degrees
when we do it with error propagation as indicated
by the little star then it comes out as 5.1 so
it's not a big increase and that isn't surprising
because we've got a reasonably large number of
specimens they're based on a reasonably large or
in some cases very large number of demagnetization
steps and they've got small mads so there isn't a
lot of uncertainty associated with these specimens
and that's reflected by only a small increase
in the um in the alpha 95 at the site level
but let's look at a contrasting
data set again from the same study
now we only have three specimens
and a relatively small number of
demagnetization steps for each specimen
and reasonably large mads and what we find
if we just calculate the site mean direction or
an alpha 95 without error propagation it's 1.9
degrees the alpha 95 do with error propagation
it becomes 8.7 degrees which is clearly a big
difference and again not surprising small number
of specimens small number of demagnetization steps
which makes the uncertainty associated
with the specimen level directions large
so whereas on the previous site most of the alpha
95 was dominated by scatter within the directions
in this case most of the alpha 95 is dominated
by the uncertainty on the individual specimens
now another example this is from some
sedimentary records from snowball etal 2013
again i'm not going to question the findings
of the paper this was simply that the data
was available and i was able to work with it um
so they were studying a swedish lake they had
four sediment cores from that lake that they were
able to place on a composite depth scale so the
four cores are represented by different colored
points they have inclination declination and mad
and then what they wanted to do to come up
with a single composite record was they used a
150-year moving average through the data where
they just used fishes statistics to estimate
the mean at each point along the record in this
150-year moving average so we basically repeated
that process but we did the error propagation for
each 150 year window and this is the result both
in terms of the inclination where you've got the
mean of the moving average in black and the 95
confidence interval in in gray for both the
inflation and the declination so what we actually
did in in this case is we were able to take the
alpha 95 error propagated version of the alpha 95
and marginalize those errors into separate errors
in the inclination and the declaration so we now
have specific confidence intervals on inflation
and declaration thanks to this error propagation
now of course snowball et al did it for four
sediment cores in a single lake but if you were
wanting to stack records from multiple lakes
you could use exactly the same process okay
you're just bringing these things together and
propagating the errors but how much of effect
did the error propagation actually have so here
i've got a plot of the alpha 95 without error
propagation if we just use his standard fischer
statistics and here's the alpha 95 with error
propagation and a one-to-one line so what you can
see for this specific case of the lake sediments
is for a lot of the samples or the the averages in
the in these 150-year windows it doesn't make that
much difference to include the error propagation
but you can see there's some samples where it does
make a big difference so in over a third of the
cases here the alpha 95 increases by more than
50 percent when we increase increase the error
propagation now the question is is that important
or not really comes down to what question you're
asking of your data okay so we can we can estimate
these uncertainties and then depending on the
inferences that you're trying to draw from your
data is really going to tell you if that change in
the uncertainty is is important or not important
now there is one kind of hurdle to this error
propagation technique and here's the example again
of how we can take samples and sites formations
up to paleomagnetic poles in this natural
kind of hierarchical fashion but once we start
working with poles we typically involve a vgp
transform so we go from our formation means
through to our poles via the vgp transform
and we know from the form of the vgp transform
that if we're assuming that for example our
data around here is fissure distributed for
example site means formation means and so on
and once we vgp transform it it will
no longer be fissure distributed
the opposite is true as well a lot of people
working in pot with poles and apparent polar
wonder paths assume that the data is fission
distributed and we know given the form of the vgp
transform if the poles are fissure distributed
that means the data that went into them for
example site means formation means can't be fishy
distributed so this actually breaks the assumption
of fissure distributed data at this point this is
something we're still working on at the moment to
try and work out how we can get past this hurdle
so it means that you can't go through the entire
hierarchy using this fischer technique because of
the need to be gp transform but all is not lost
okay here's an example uh from a paper by camp
setal where they're looking at late ligocene polls
and they had they measured or estimated a new poll
and collated polls from a series of publications
that they then average together so what we've got
in the figure here is their poll and a collection
of polls that are then averaged using fishes
statistics so even if because of the vgp transform
we haven't been able to propagate uncertainty up
all the way from the specimen level maybe you just
start your uncertainty propagation when you start
combining poles together that's okay it's not
a complete error propagation but it's better
than doing no error propagation at all so these
are the collections of all the polls collated by
camp satell they've got the poll that their new
poll that they estimated in 2007 and then their
collections of polls from the literature again
if you combine these with just traditional fischer
statistics you get an alpha 95 on the mean pole of
four degrees with error propagation it's four and
a half degrees so it's only gone up a little bit
you may say what's half a degree again it depends
on the question that you're asking of your data
and importantly if you actually do it with the
error propagation you know that you're not going
to be shocked dealing with a traditional mean and
then suddenly discover that the uncertainties have
a huge influence so of course it's always better
to work with error propagated estimates if you can
but if we refer back to this
um data from the collation or
the collection of camps that are what we
can see is it doesn't look particularly
fishy distributed it's kind of elongated
like this and i calculated the best fitting
fischer distribution to the data which is given
by this dash circle here and what you can see is
it's really quite different to the data itself so
it looks like this data aren't fisher distributed
we could imagine bootstrapping instead and
the bootstrap allows us to estimate means and
uncertainties associated with them but only when
the number of observations is relatively large
here the number of observations is kind of
small there isn't some magic number that
you can say if i have this many observations the
bootstrap will work but what we do know is that
if you only have a small number of observations
the bootstrap's going to be pretty unreliable
now of course looking at these kind of
distributions of paleo planting poles
is kind of challenging because they do have
systematic biases in them for example if a
place is migrating through time and then i'm
looking at poles estimated through a certain
time window then i might see that that trend of
the poles that corresponds to the plate motion
so distributions of poles are kind of tricky
to deal with but generally people assume
everything's fissure distributed looking
at the data here maybe that isn't the case
but what about psb i was talking about the site
averaging in the golan heights i talked about the
lake sediments in in sweden where that was about
averaging psv so is psv fishy distributed well
the simple answer is no okay so we have these
um giant gaussian process models of um secular
variation there's a number of different models
available and again a really nice paper here by
kokoloff where they were able to actually map
out what the distribution of psv directions
is for these ggp models as a function of latitude
so this is the distribution for 0 degrees
all the way up to 90 degrees and
i should say they're symmetrical
about the equator so we only need to in this
case consider positive latitudes um clearly
according to the ggp models these distributions
of psv are not fissure distributed again that
might be a bit of a problem if we're assuming
fischer distributions in our error propagation
but will the fischer statistics still work so i
set out to test this and i took one of the ggp
models at tk03 which was torx and kent in 2003 and
the nice thing about these models is if you select
a certain latitude you know from a model exactly
what the true or the time average field direction
is for the model okay so we can select a latitude
and we actually know what the time average field
is at that location we can then draw n random
directions from the model that kind of simulate
our observations of psv we can estimate an alpha
95 using fissure statistics and then we ask is the
true mean direction actually within that alpha
95 or not and we repeat that for example 1000
times so if the fish's statistics are providing
a reliable estimate then what we'd expect is that
the true field mean field direction falls within
the alpha 95 95 of the time so this is what i
did with my simulation so i did it for different
latitudes and different numbers of observations
you can see here i'm dealing with really small
numbers of observations that are kind of typical
of some psv studies so what happens when i'm just
working with three observations and equals three
four observations five observations and ten
observations and what you can see is we're hoping
for a value of 95 percent and you can see all
these values are pretty close to 95 so even though
psv data are clearly not fissure distributed
fischer's statistics work well in terms of
estimating the mean and the alpha 95 of the
observations even when n is very small for example
n equals three now if n was large enough you
could just bootstrap and not worry about it but
in a lot of cases a lot of studies bootstrapping
is not feasible because we just don't have enough
observations so for psv at least it seems assuming
efficient distribution is going to work just fine
so just to finish off um like i said here's the
paper where everything's in and we have online
calculators for doing these analyses they're
pretty simple you could code them up in excel
if you wanted to but we've also got the online
functions if you want them so there's code in
github but also these online calculators where
for example this is a specimen level just for
each specimen you give the declaration inclination
number of demagnetization steps used in the pca
analysis what's the mad was the fit anchored or
not and then it'll output the result that tells
you what the mean direction is and the alpha 95
with the uncertainty included and if you just
use traditional uh statistic fischer statistics
without uncertainty propagation you can see the
alpha 95s are quite different in this case okay
so that's all online and available so to conclude
hopefully we've i can convince you that we've
developed a scheme for simple hierarchical error
propagation and all it is is it takes our existing
framework of fischer's statistics and adds
a waiting term to it it's nothing more than
that it works from the specimen level upwards
so as long as you have inclination declination
mad number of demagnetization steps used in the
pca and was it an anchored or an anchored fit
then you can do the specimen level uncertainty
it can be applied to legacy data if you have this
information if you don't then you can just start
the error propagation later on in the sequence for
example when you start dealing with combinations
of site means vicious statistics appear to
be appropriate to handle psv directions when
bootstrapping is infeasible and as i just said
we've got code available python code and online
calculators which you can find by my website which
is the address here so i will stop there thank you
thank you very much steve give dave
a virtual round of applause for
um interesting talk i've certainly got a
couple of questions uh to throw your way um
we can open the floor uh to anybody else with some
questions so if you um just want to raise your
hand through through zoom and you can ask dave a
question otherwise i'll just jump in with my one
well i mean i'll kick it off then um so at the
start you're you're saying that you know when you
add two fischer distributions together they're not
fischer distributing but we can approximate them
as being fisher distributed i mean does does
that approximation hold if we're summing up an
arbitrary number official distributions or or does
it start to break down so what you yeah i should
in the paper we clarify this um and it's also what
is the best matching or best approximating fischer
distribution so it actually uh specifically
uses the callback of libra divergence metric
so we can actually from that calculate
how much deviation there is a way from
the sum to the fischer distribution
that we're approximating it with
so we can actually we actually have
a divergence measure to quantify that
okay is that then is it sort of recommended to use
that then to assess whether or not the assumption
is valid and whether or not the error propagation
is is valid then yeah so at the moment we we for
example don't provide threshold values to say
this is acceptable this is not acceptable i'm not
i'm not a big fan of these magic values that on
one side of it you're perfectly okay and then you
take a tiny step over and suddenly everything's
gone wrong you know so a little bit of judgment
is required on these deviations and what is a big
deviation what is a small deviation so at least i
can say we can measure the level of deviation
then how you choose to use that is a slightly
different question that i'm not going to attempt
to answer so that's a very pragmatic approach
and so does everyone else have
some some questions for for dave
this is probably a dumb question so um but when
you're talking about the challenge of going from
sight mean directions to the vgp transform
uh isn't it reversible so couldn't you just
i guess why can't you just uh say get your
vgps and then convert to like a common site
main direction and then presumably that's now
fisherian or is that not gonna work for the
error propagation yeah i'm not i'm not
sure about that so i i think probably the
the best way to do it is a similar step
where you do the transform and it's like
and i think this is what you suggested and then
you find the best fisher fit to that transform
um and maybe that works fine or maybe you
have something that's clearly not fisheries
um and i think that's where people actually
need to be looking at their data and checking
what's happening and actually making this even
if it's just a graphical assessment to say
no this clearly isn't for shearing anymore i
shouldn't be assuming efficient distribution
but i think that's the natural way to get through
the transform is to approximate everything as
fischer transform it again and then find the
best approximating fischer distribution again
um and i think maybe we need to
run some simulations to just see
how much of an issue that could actually be or if
it's a reasonable assumption to make we work with
um people over in the department of
statistics here at anu who are experts
on statistics on spheres and i showed them the
vgp transform and asked them if they were able to
work out what efficient district or the equation
for efficient distribution would be once it's been
vgp transformed and i got a i got a one sentence
email reply which would be this is not obvious
now considering these people are world experts
in these things i i think my chances of coming
up with it are slim to none and it sounds like it
might be a difficult problem to try to tackle um
so maybe just sticking with a best fitting
fischer distribution might be the way forward
that makes sense thank you
and do you have any any other questions
to throw dave's way excuse me this
is from osaka and
distribution yeah well that's
a good question it could be
almost meaningless i mean it yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah it it depends so i guess it depends how much
your data deviates from um efficient distribution
so we saw in the case of psv that even though the
data isn't fissure distributed the fischer's
statistics will still still do a good job and
we can readily test that numerically because we
have these ggp models i think it's more difficult
to test with um poles because yeah we can't
really simulate poles in an obvious way that we
can do these kind of um you know monte carlo type
assessments of of how well the things are behaving
so it's like all statistical processes
though if if your data don't meet the
assumptions of the statistics then your
statistics will give you a spurious result
so that's always important for the users
to remember that they can't just blindly
put the numbers in there and expect what they
get to actually mean anything you know this is
old computer science adage of garbage in
equals garbage out so you know i i can't really
comment on that i think it may be about the
community having a more detailed conversation
i know lisa for example would say
you should be bootstrapping um
i believe yeah but you know one of one
of the limitations of the bootstrap is
it doesn't have any paramagnet paramagnetic any
parametric parametric electric assumption but
you have to have a large enough sample size
in order for it to be um robust yeah so if
dealing with n equals three n equals four
that's something you can't bootstrap um
because you're lacking information in your sample
you have to replace that with information your
assumptions which is with distributed or so on you
know another point is that some kind of hierarchy
hierarchy hierarchy uh statistical system
the the cause of error is different in
each hierarchy so alpha 95 or k are different
in each hierarchy are there any any way to
solve these hierarchical differences in the uh
cause of error well so so in the hierarchy you
you re-estimate kappa and r at each step in the
hierarchy depending on if you're dealing with
fights or formations or so on so it's
a continuous process of re-estimating
the parameters each at each level in the hierarchy
again just by these standard fischer
statistics with the weight term included yeah i
quite good right but the estimate of k or
delta is a little bit different so each step
k and or delta must be different so the
uh whole k does not mean anything right
well so what you would have for example for
each if you do a combination of site means
each site mean would have a kappa or a k value and
then when you um and an r value associated with it
and then when you combine into the formation you
would use those kappas and r's to formulate a new
fischer distribution for your formation
and that distribution has its own cap
and r so then if you've got that for some
formations you're just combining them so it
really is just a re-estimation of each
site each formation and and so on yeah
yeah so thank you very much especially i'll
just keep a quick eye on on our decline
sorry no that's not a problem um does anybody
else have a question to to throw uh dave's way
i have one very quick one dave can this the same
principles be applied to inclination-only data
um good question i had a
at a first guess i think they probably could
because the the statistics for inclination data is
still based on fissure distributions but it's
integra it's integrated over declination so
the yeah so the declination is kind of integrated
out so i think it it should be possible if that's
of interest to people then you know i can
i can take a look more deeply at it i think
there's a whole whole uh drilling community
that might uh might find that quite useful
now could you just rotate everything to have an
average declaration yeah yeah there we go started
excellent it's the kind of thing while we're here
i'll say yes it's it's simple it's easy and then
um i'll go quiet on that for about 18 months so
yeah and then get a one-line email saying it's not
very obvious it's not very obvious yeah excellent
thank you very much steve uh for a great talk give
dave another um virtual round of applause
through uh through our zoom uh and just before we
uh come to a close um just allow me to um wrap
up with a last little bit of housekeeping um so
we're going to have a a short break um for
iaga um we don't want to to overlap with the
other conference um but we'll be back in september
and september 8th uh with a speaker who's who's to
be confirmed uh we have somebody lined up but
we don't want to announce them until they say
absolutely yes uh and then we've got a couple more
uh presenters on this eastern hemisphere european
uh time slot and then in october we're actually
going to move back to um the european americas
time slots for for for the remainder of
the year so apologies to people who will be
in bed at that time but um you'll be able
to catch up on on our magnet seminars with
uh with the youtube channel and as always we're
looking for for uh future speakers um we've
filled up our schedule for 2021 so we're looking
for anybody who's interested in in presenting
uh next year and as always we're we're really
want to encourage um early career researchers
so please just get in touch as i mentioned um
you can catch up with all the magnet seminars
on our youtube channel so thank you all very
much for for joining magnets today cheers